Preliminary Inventory to the William A. Niskanen Papers, 1959-1985
Hoover Institution Archives
William A. Niskanen Papers,
1959-1985
81043
Niskanen, William A., 1933-
76 manuscript boxes (31.7 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, studies, speeches, conference proceedings, minutes, press briefings, statistics, circulars, and printed matter, relating to American government administration and budgeting during the presidential administration of Richard M. Nixon, movements to limit taxation in the United States, and governmental economic policy during the presidential administration of Ronald Reagan.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Access Points
Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-; United States. Office of Management and Budget.; Budget--United States.; Public administration--United States.; Taxation--United States.; United States--Politics and government.; United States--Politics and government--1969-1974.; Conservatism.; Reagan, Ronald.; Council of Economic Advisers (U.S.); United States--Politics and government--1981-1989.; United States--Economic policy--1981-1993.; United States--Economic conditions--1945-; Economists.
Biography
American economist; assistant director for evaluation, United States Office of Management and Budget, 1970-1972; member, Council of Economic Advisers, 1981-1985.
Container List
- Biographical and miscellaneous file, 1961-1973 (Box 1)
  - Biographical material
  - Consulting
  - Defense (Department of) memoranda, 1962-1964
  - Pending personal matters
  - Personal correspondence
  - Personal employment
    - 1961-1970
    - 1970-1973 (Box 2)
  - Public Choice Society
- Correspondence, 1959-1980
  - 1959-1964
  - 1965-1969 (Box 3)
  - 1970-1971 (Box 4)
  - 1972-1973 (Box 5)
  - 1973-1974 (Box 6)
  - 1974-1975 (Box 7)
  - 1975-1976 (Box 8)
  - 1976-1977 (Box 9)
  - 1977-1978 (Box 10)
  - 1979-1980 (Box 11)
- Engagements, 1968-1972 (Box 12)
  - 1968-1971
  - 1971 (Box 13)
  - 1972 (Box 14)
- U.S. Office of Management and Budget file, 1970-1972
  - Administrative and related services
  - Agency hearing schedules
  - Agriculture
  - American Enterprise Institute
  - Analytic structures (Box 15)
  - Atomic Energy Commission
  - Balance of payments
  - Budget, 1971-1973
  - Budget costs
  - Budget message
  - Budget outlay totals
  - Budget procedures (Box 16)
  - Budget process
  - Budget reform
  - Budget Review Division
  - Budget statistics
  - Civil defense
  - Civil rights
  - Civil service
  - Commerce
  - Computer
  - Congress
  - Congressional action report
  - Consumer affairs (Box 17)
  - Corps of Engineers (of the U.S. Army)
  - Cost estimating
  - Credit programs
  - Cut exercise
  - Defense
  - Defense Economic Analysis Council
  - Defense management (Box 18)
  - Defense profits study
  - Director's meeting
  - Director's status
  - Disaster programs
  - Domestic Council
  - Drugs
  - Economic conditions, 1970-1972
  - Economic Development Administration (Box 19)
    - General
    - Regional development
  - Economic report
  - Education, 1970-1971
  - Educational Program in Systematic Analysis
  - Employment discrimination (Box 20)
  - Energy policy
  - Environment
    - 1970-1971
    - 1971-1972 (Box 21)
  - Evaluation Division (of the Office of Management and Budget)
    - Memoranda
    - Staff meetings
  - Expenditure cuts
  - Expenditure status
  - Export-Import Bank
  - Federal Reports
  - Federal-state relations (Box 22)
  - Feldman, Paul
  - Financial management
  - Fiscal policy
  - Foreign economic development
  - General Accounting Office reports
  - General Services Administration
  - Government activities abroad (Box 23)
  - Government employment
  - Government pay
  - Government pension
  - Government procurement
  - Grant management
  - Health
  - Health, Education and Welfare, Department of
  - Housing (Box 24)
    - General
    - Military families
  - Housing and Urban Development, Department of
  - Income distribution
  - Income maintenance
  - Indemnification study (Box 25)
  - Indians
  - Interest rate
  - Interior, Department of the
  - International
  - International economics
  - Issue letters (Fiscal Year 1973)
  - Issues process
  - Jobs study (Box 26)
  - Joint Economic Committee (of the U.S. Congress)
  - Justice
  - Lead tax
  - Leasing
    - General
    - Automobiles
  - Legislative Reorganization Act of 1970
  - Legislative tracking system
  - Loan programs (Box 27)
  - McKinsey study
  - Management improvement
  - Management information systems
  - Manpower
    - General
    - Military
  - Migrants
  - Minority business enterprise
  - National Aeronautical and Space Administration
  - National growth policy
  - National Institute of Mental Health
  - National Science Foundation (Box 28)
  - Natural resources
  - Niemela
  - North American Rockwell Corporation proposal
  - Office of Economic Opportunity
  - Office of Management and Budget
    - Circulars
    - Draft circular on planning, programming and budgeting
    - Institutional problems
    - Memoranda (Box 29)
    - Press releases
    - Seminars
    - Staff
  - Office of Science and Technology
  - Oil and gas policy
  - Organization and Management Systems Division (of the Office of Management and Budget)
  - Outstanding White House actions
  - Performance measurement systems (Box 30)
  - Planning, programming and budgeting system
    - General
    - 1970
    - 1971-1972 (Box 31)
  - Policy implementation review
  - Pollution
  - Postal Service
  - Potential Evaluation Division staff (Box 32)
  - Presidential technology
  - Private pensions
  - Privatization study
  - Productivity
  - Program Analysis Division (of the Institute for Defense Analyses) publications
  - Program budgeting (Box 33)
  - Program on technology and society
  - Program overview
  - Project Advisory Group (of the Department of the Army)
  - Property management
  - Public affairs schools (Box 34)
  - Public interest lobby study
  - Public investment
  - Public service employment
  - Real property
  - Regional councils
  - Regional development
  - Regulations and Purchasing Review Board
  - Regulatory agencies
  - Reorganization plans
  - Republican activities
  - Research and development
  - Research and development (Box 35)
  - Research Council
  - Revenue-sharing
    - 1970
    - 1971 (Box 36)
  - Review: The Budget's New Clothes
  - Rolling budget system
  - Science
  - Security (Box 37)
  - Social research and development
  - Social security
  - Space
  - Special Analysis S
  - Spring planning review for 1974
  - Spring preview (Fiscal Year 1973)
  - State, Department of
  - State and local government (Box 38)
  - Statistics
  - Taxes
  - Tennis
  - Transportation
    - General
    - General (Box 39)
    - 1969-1970
  - Travel
  - Treasury, Department of the
  - U.S. Military Research and Development Management Panel meetings
  - Urban Institute (Box 40)
  - Urban studies
  - User charges
  - Veterans Administration
  - Visitors
  - Vocational education
  - Voluntary action
  - Volunteer military
  - Wage bill subsidy
  - Water Resources Council (Box 41)
  - Weekly briefing reports
  - Weekly briefing reports (Box 42)
  - Weinberger (Caspar) task
  - White House requests
  - Chronological file
    - 1970-1971
    - 1971-1972 (Box 43)
  - Circulars
    - A-11
    - A-25 (Box 44)
    - A-34
    - A-44
    - A-46
    - A-76
    - A-76 (Box 45)
    - A-94
    - A-95
    - Leasing - Drafts, 1971
- Tax limitation file, 1973-1980
  - California - Tax Reduction Task Force
  - California - Tax Reduction Task Force (Box 46)
  - Federal government (Box 47)
    - General
    - Correspondence
    - Proposed constitutional amendment
    - Proposed constitutional amendment (Box 48)
  - Michigan
    - General
    - General (Box 49)
    - Ford Motor Company correspondence
    - Headlee, Richard (Box 50)
    - Implementation of Proposal E
  - Various states (Box 51)